Alumni Association; Records ua801
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University at Albany, SUNY Alumni Association Records1851-2011
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Alumni Association of the University at Albany, SUNY
ua801
67.68 cubic ft.
The State University of New York at Albany Alumni Association Records document the day-to-day operations of the Alumni Association from the 1850s to the early 21st Century.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of a small number of folders in Series 3: Subject Files noted on the finding aid below.
Acquisition Information
The State University of New York at Albany Alumni Association transferred its files to M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in a series of acquisitions. The Alumni Association still retains recent files for its own use.
Biographical Sketch
The State University of New York at Albany Alumni Association was founded in 1849 under the name of "The Association of Graduates of the New York Normal School." Its original intent was to keep track of the addresses and professions of graduates, and to organize support for the school in its dealings with New York State government. Under Corresponding Secretary William Phelps the Association started an educational placement bureau to help graduates. The Association met biannually and would attempt to meet for "jubilees" and reunions. The Association was dormant during the Civil War and not revived till 1872. The following year in 1873 the Association adopted a new constitution. In 1890, concurrent with the renaming of the school, the Association voted to update the name to "Association of Graduates of the New York State Normal School and the New York State Normal College." The organization financed and provided information for the first two histories of the school published in 1884 and 1895.
In 1883 the Association took up its first fund-raising effort when the group raised $5,000 to pay for an "Alumni Memorial Window" for the school’s new Willett Street building. In 1894 the Association raised funds for a "Soldiers Memorial Tablet" to honor the school's Civil War dead, and, after the 1906 fire that destroyed the Willett Street Building, the Memorial Window and tablet, the organization engaged in a new campaign for a replacement Soldier’s Memorial Tablet. Subsequently the Association raised funds for tablets to honor school World War I and World War II dead. Instead of replacing the Alumni Memorial Window, the Association chose to raise $10,000 to fund a graduate scholarship in education. The fund-raising took over 40 years as the first Albert N. Husted Scholarship was not awarded until 1948. In the meantime, during the 1910s and 1920s many individuals and classes established Alumni Association small loan funds for students.
In addition to the main Alumni Association, graduates established regional branches in such places as New York City, Long Island, Rochester, Eastern and Western New York, Florida, California, and Washington, D.C. These chapters frequently held their own events and sponsored activities for alumni in their respective geographic location.
In 1921 the Association started a Dormitory Committee/Residence Hall Building Fund with the goal of raising funds to purchase land and build dormitories with alumni money—Pierce Hall for women opened in 1935 and Sayles Hall for men opened in 1941. Fund-raising and the purchase of property was carried out through the newly formed Benevolent Association which was incorporated in New York in 1926. In 1967 the State of New York purchased those dormitories and funds from the purchase were put into alumni funded scholarships. The Alumni Association based its operations out of the Benevolent Association office from 1929 until 1962 when it became part of University Administration.
There were other substantial fund-raising endeavors carried out by the Alumni Association. In 1964 alumni organized to build the symbol of the University's Uptown Campus, the musical Carillon. In 1972 the Alumni Association began a drive to build Alumni House, also on the new Uptown Campus. The organization also raised money at various times for scholarship funds. In 1972 the Alumni Association established the Annual Fund as the main fund-raising effort. In 1982 this was transferred to the University at Albany Fund, Inc., created out of a merger between the Benevolent Association, the University Foundation and Annual Fund of the Alumni Association to serve as one unified University fund-raising operation.
The Alumni Association updated its name again in 1964 to the University at Albany Alumni Association and was incorporated, under Education law 501(c)(3), as a non-profit education corporation.
The collection also documents other initiatives for alumni undertaken by the organization. There are publications written for and about alumni, featuring class notes and updates. As in earlier periods, the Alumni Association continued to plan Alumni Day and class reunions. During the 1970s and 1980s the Alumni office offered travel packages ranging from weekend excursions to view foliage in the Adirondacks to multi-week adventures in destinations in Europe and Asia. In recent years as the Alumni community grew so did Association responsibilities. The organization provides alumni with important business and personal connections as well as plans events, such as the Big Purple Growl and Homecoming. The Big Purple Growl is a midyear home basketball game that is accompanied by other events, including a feast, and heavily attended by alumni.
Scope and Contents
The State University of New York at Albany Alumni Association Records document the day-to-day operations and special event planning of the organization. The Alumni Association is a semi-independent, incorporated entity on campus that coordinates alumni outreach and supports the University community through fund-raising and advocacy.
The collection includes meeting minutes and agendas, financial records, correspondence, photographs, publications, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia. While the bulk of materials dates from the 1960s through the 1980s, there also are notable 19th and early 20th Century records, including materials from reunions, correspondence, records of the building of the first residence halls, publications, and administrative files.
Please note that two series contain records of semi-independent organizations directly related to alumni and the Alumni Association; the Benevolent Association (Series 6) and the Theatre Alumni Association (Series 7). See each series description for additional information and history of these groups.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1-7 are arranged chronologically and Series 8 is arranged alphabetically.
Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States; Fund raising; Telephone fund raising; Dormitories; Class reunions; State University of New York at Albany--History; Scholarships; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Societies, etc.--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Periodicals; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Societies, etc.--Administration; Agendas (administrative records); Appointment books; Attendance lists; Audits; Calendars; Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Financial Records; Form letters; Invitations; Ledgers (account books); Memorandum; Minutes; Photographs; Page proofs; Quarterlies (publications); Reports; Newsletters; Web Archives; State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Albany. Alumni Association; State University of New York at Albany. Benevolent Association; State University of New York at Albany. Theatre Alumni Association; State University of New York at Albany. Theatre Dept.
- Administration, 1873-1997; Undated; 1; 5.32 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials pertaining to the Board of Directors and the administration of the Alumni Association, including founding documents, such as the charter and constitution. The earliest Board of Directors meeting minutes are bound volumes. By the end of the 1970s the minutes are loose notes belonging to specific individuals. The minutes may also include such supplemental materials as correspondence, agendas and financial papers. The annual report was available for the Annual Meeting, which was open to all Alumni Association members. Financial records for the Alumni Association are found in this series in ledgers, financial statements and Treasurer’s reports. Loose items from bound volumes have been removed and stored in separate, appropriately labeled folders.
  - Secretary's Book, 1873-1917 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Alumni Day Programs of Menus included in Secretary's Book, 1873-1917 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence included in Secretary's Book, 1873-1917 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings included in Secretary's Book, 1873-1917 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Vouchers included in Secretary's Book, 1873-1917 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1876-1881 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Treasurer's Book, 1898-1910 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - New York State Normal College Alumni Association Limited Charter, 1907 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Oversized 1)
  - Beneficiary Aid Fund included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Clippings included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Speeches and Press Releases included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Half-Century Club Materials included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Husted Fellowship Fund Materials included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Programs included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Residence Hall Materials included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Risley Memorial Award included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - Treasurer's Reports included in Secretary's Book, 1917-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Eastern New York Branch of Alumni Association-Minutes and Supplemental Materials, 1919-1930 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Minutes of the Graduate Council of the Alumni Association, 1919-1953 (Oversized 1)
  - Minutes, Reports and Correspondence included in the Graduate Council of the Alumni Association Ledger, 1919-1953 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Annual Meeting, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1927-1939 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Inclusions from Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1927-1939 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Eastern New York Branch of Alumni Association-Minutes and Supplemental Materials, 1929-1970 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 23-24)
  - Constitution, 1920s (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Correspondence included in Receipts and Disbursement Ledger, 1931-1933 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - Reports included in Receipts and Disbursements Ledger, 1933-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1939-1942 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - Inclusions from Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1927-1939 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Receipts and Disbursements, 1931-1933 (Oversized 2)
  - Receipts and Disbursements, 1933-1940 (Oversized 2)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements, 1935-1936 (Oversized 4, Folder 1)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements, 1935-1936 (Oversized 4, Folder 2)
  - Secretary's Book/Alumni Day, 1940-1948 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Clippings included in Secretary's Book, 1940-1948 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 31)
  - Treasurer's General Account, 1940-1955 (Oversized 2)
  - Cash Operating Account, 1942-1966 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 32-33)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 34)
  - Inclusions from Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 35)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1945-1957 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 36)
  - Inclusions from Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1945-1957 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 37)
  - Executive Board Meeting, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 38)
  - Secretary's Book, 1949-1954 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 39)
  - Budget, 1949; 1953-1959 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 40)
  - Secretary's Book, 1954-1956 (Oversized 1)
  - Reports and Summaries included in Secretary's Book, 1954-1956 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 41)
  - Alumni Day and Quarterly Report to Executive Secretary, 1955-1958 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 42)
  - Treasurer's General Account, 1955-1959 (Oversized 3)
  - Graduate Council Minutes, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 43)
  - Ledger-Alumni Association, 1959-1960 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 44)
  - Miriam Rider Correspondence with Alumni Day and Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1959-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 45)
  - Progress Report of Study Committee, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 46)
  - Board of Director's Special Meeting, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 47)
  - Balance Sheets, 1961-1970 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 48)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes and Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 49)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes and Annual Report, 1962-1965 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Statement of Funds, 1962-1968 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1963-1964 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Financial Statements, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Report to the Executive Committee of the Association by the Alumni Council Planning Committee for Project Carillon, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Financial Statements, 1964-1965 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Incorporation Documents, 1964-1965 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Constitutional and By-Laws Revisions, 1965; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Financial Statements, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Board of Director's Handbook, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Financial Statements, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes and Alumni Office Annual Report, 1966-1969 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1967 June 10 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Adjusting Journal Entries-Peat, Marwick Mitchell, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - Financial Statements, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Statement of Objective and Goals, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Alumni Office Annual Report, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Ledger Sheets, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Financial Records, including Tax Returns and Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Financial Statements, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 23)
  - Alumni Office Annual Report, 1968-1969 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 24)
  - Financial Statements, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Financial Statements, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - Board of Director's Members, ca. 1970 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Financial Statements, 1970-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Annual Report of the Alumni Association, 1970-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 31)
  - Alumni Council Meeting Minutes, 1963-1964; 1968; 1970-1974; 1978-1979; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 32)
  - Financial Statements, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 33)
  - Financial Records Binder, 1971-1972 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 34-35)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1971-1972 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 36)
  - Financial Statements, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 37)
  - Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 38)
  - Financial Ledger, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 39-40)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 41)
  - Robert Fairbanks-Treasurer of Alumni Association, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 42)
  - Annual Alumni Association Meeting, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 43)
  - Financial Statements, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 44)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1973-1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 45)
  - Annual Alumni Association Meeting, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 46)
  - Board of Directors Memo, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 47)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 48)
  - Financial Statement, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 49)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1974-1975 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 50)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 51)
  - Financial Statement, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 52)
  - Annual Report to Executive Secretary, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 53)
  - Report of Executive Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 54)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 55)
  - Board of Directors Ballots, 1975; 1977-1980; 1985-1986 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1976-1977 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Annual Report of the Alumni Association, 1976-1980 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1977 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Financial Statement, 1977 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1977-1978 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes-Sue Emborsky's file, 1977-1979 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1978 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Financial Statement, 1978 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Revision of Alumni Association By-Laws, 1978 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1978-1979 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1979 March 31 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Gary L. Jones, Director of Alumni Affairs, 1979 June 23 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Gary L. Jones, Board of Directors Meeting, 1979 September 15 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - Gary L. Jones, Board of Directors Meeting, 1979 December 01 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1979 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Financial Statement, 1979 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1979-1980 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Sample Packet, Board of Directors Meeting, 1980 June 21 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1980 September 06 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1980 December 06 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 23)
  - Sorrell Chesin, Correspondence about Board of Director's Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 24)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Financial Statement, 1980 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1980-1981 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes and Report to President of Alumni Association, 1980-1989 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - Marsha J. McCarthy '67, Board of Directors Meeting, 1981 March 28 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1981 September 19 (Box 3 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1981 December 05 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Sorrell Chesin, Correspondence with Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Memos, 1981 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 2-3)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1981 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Financial Statement, 1981 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1981-1982 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1981-1982 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1982 March 27 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1982 June 12 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 9-10)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1982 October 23 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1982 December 04 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Sorrell Chesin, Correspondence with Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Memos, 1982 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Financial Statements, 1982-1983 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1982-1983 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1983 May 13 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 16-17)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1983 August 27 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1983 November 19 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Financial Statements, 1983-1984 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1983-1984 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1984 February 25 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1984 May 11 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 23)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1984 August 25 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 24)
  - Financial Statements, 1984-1985 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1984-1985 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1985 March 09 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1985 June 07 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1985 September 24 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Financial Statements, 1985-1986 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1985-1986 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 31)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1986 January 11 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 32)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1986 March 15 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 33)
  - Lorna W. Reamer, Board of Directors Meeting, 1986 June 06 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 34)
  - Ann G. Begam, Board of Directors Meeting, 1986 September 20 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 35)
  - Financial Statements, 1986-1987 (Box 4 (1-Administration), Folder 36)